A Guide to the Wallace Company Records, 1783-1975 (bulk 1875-1945)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Wallace Company Records, 1783-1975 (bulk 1875-1945)
The Library of Virginia
44017
41 cu. ft. and 249 volumes.
John G. Wallace III.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John G. Wallace IV, Chesapeake, Virginia 23323.
Biographical and Historical Information
George Thomas Wallace, only son of William Wallace of Norfolk County, Virginia, was born near Great Bridge on 4 April 1812. William Wallace was collector of tolls and agent of the Dismal Swamp Canal at Deep Creek. George T. Wallace married Elizabeth McIntosh Curtis, daughter of Drayton Mills Curtis and Mary Calvert Walke, in 1835. He began to buy property in the 1840's on the east side of the canal about halfway down its length at its intersection with the North West Canal. By 1855, his holdings in the area amounted to almost 14,000 acres. He built a large home called "Glencoe" in 1841. His sons, John Gallaudette Wallace (1840-1910) and William Curtis Wallace (1842-1864), both served in the Confederate army during the Civil War. George T. Wallace and John G. Wallace entered into partnership, under the name Wallace and Son, in the lumber and milling business along the Dismal Swamp Canal, and in eastern North Carolina. A sawmill was constructed on the west bank of the Dismal Swamp Canal, and they milled the abundant juniper, pine, poplar, and cedar into shingles, rails, ties, and telegraph poles. They also built a store building on the east side of the canal, which also functioned as a company store for the lumbermen.
Following the death of George T. Wallace, the name of the firm was changed to the Wallace Company, and John G. Wallace began to cultivate the family's large landholdings in Norfolk County towards the growing of corn, potatoes, and soybeans, especially on their plantation called "Dover." The produce was sold to commission merchants locally, as well as in Baltimore, Philadelphia, and New York City. John G. Wallace married Vernonica McGehee (1842-1907) of Louisa County, Virginia, on 15 February 1865. They had five children, including: 1) Elizabeth Curtis Wallace (1865-1932); 2) George Thomas Wallace, Jr. (1868-1932); 3) William McGehee Wallace (b. 1871); 4) John Gallaudette Wallace II (1877-1945); and 5) Veronica McGehee Wallace (1882-1943).
John G. Wallace II continued the business following his father's death in 1910, although it was not his primary occupation, and the firm was dissolved shortly before World War II. "Dover" was sold to the United States government in 1941. Wallace served one term in the Virginia House of Delegates, was treasurer of Norfolk County, and was employed as sales manager for the Southern Produce Company. He married Maria Mildred Wilson on 9 June 1909. He died at Wallaceton on 30 March 1945.
Scope and Content
Records, 1783-1975, of the Wallace Company, located in Wallaceton, Norfolk County, Virginia, a lumber milling business, and later growers and shippers of corn, potatoes and soybeans. The firm was previously known as Wallace and Son. The collection also contains records of Wallace Brothers, agents for various manufacturers of mechanical goods. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1875-1945. Includes correspondence, subject files, financial records, and maps, plans, and drawings.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1847-1970., Extent: 22 boxes. (Box 1-22)
  There is a small amount of pre-Civil War correspondence containing letters mostly written by Elizabeth (Curtis) Wallace to relatives in Ohio. Subjects include politics and slavery, and family news. There is also a letter written in 1865 by George T. Wallace (1812-1889) regarding his views on Northerners following the end of the war.
  The correspondence covering the period 1865 to 1890 relates to the business activities of George T. Wallace and his son John G. Wallace (1840-1910), in their lumber business, specifically the cutting, milling, sale, purchase, shipment, and receipt of juniper, yellow pine, poplar and cedar shingles, rails, ties, and telegraph poles in Tidewater Virginia and North Carolina, under the name Wallace and Son. Subjects include business dealings with other lumber manufacturers, including Richmond Cedar Works, Baird and Roper, and the John L. Roper Lumber Company, and commission merchants in Virginia, as well as in Baltimore, New York City, and Philadelphia.
  Other topics include boundary disputes, land purchases and entries, shipments of equipment and supplies, order inquiries, prices current and market reports, employment inquiries, bank notices, and legal and tax matters. There are also letters from various Wallace property overseers concerning work being performed at the different Wallace properties.
  There is a significant amount of correspondence related to the 1885 failure of Bain and Brother, a banking house in Portsmouth, Virginia, and the involvement of The Wallace Company in its collapse. Much of it relates to protested checks, and letters from trustees that were named to settle the accounts of the banking firm. The letters written during this period also document efforts to by Wallace to secure financing to continue his operations by selling bonds and mortgaging property.
  Following the death of George T. Wallace in 1889, the name of the firm was changed to The Wallace Company, and it began to move away from lumber manufacturing and into the growing and sale of corn, potatoes, and soybeans, mainly produced on the family plantations "Glencoe" and "Dover." Much of the post-1900 correspondence is with various commission merchants regarding orders, shipments, and sales of Wallace Company produce.
  Other subjects include the dredging and enlargement of the Dismal Swamp Canal in 1896, settlement of the estate of John G. Wallace, the sale of "Dover" to the federal government during World War II, the dissolution of The Wallace Company by family members, the purchase of the Dismal Swamp Canal by the federal government, and the plight of the Depression-era farmer. There is also some correspondence related to John G Wallace II (1877-1945) and his term in the Virginia House of Delegates, as well as the settlement of the estate of his brother, George T. Wallace, Jr. (1868-1932).
  There is a group of business records of Wallace Brothers, agents for various manufacturers of mechanical goods (Boxes 14-16). The firm was founded around 1897 by the sons of John G. Wallace - George T. Wallace, Jr., William McGehee Wallace (b. 1871), and John G. Wallace II. The business was located on Granby Street in Norfolk, and sold automobiles and tractors, including the "Locomobile," typewriters, photographic supplies, bicycles, gasoline motors, sound equipment, including the "Gramophone," and musical instruments. In addition to correspondence, there are bills of lading, circulars, flyers, invoices, and price lists. There are three groups of records, 1897-1902, 1898, and 1900-1902. It is not clear why this filing arrangement exists. Within these three groups, the records are filed alphabetically by company name or surname of the correspondent. Most of the material is from companies whose products were sold by Wallace Brothers, rather than the purchasers of the goods.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1851 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1854 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1857 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1860? (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1865 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1870 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1871 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1873 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1874 (April) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1874 (May) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1874 (June) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1874 (October) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1875 (May) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1875 (June) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1875 (July) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1875 (August) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1875 (September) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1875 (November) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1876 (February) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1876 (August) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1876 (September) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1876 (October) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1876 (November) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1877 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1879 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1880 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1881 (January) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1881 (April) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1881 (June) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1881 (July) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1881 (August) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1881 (September) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1881 (October) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 1881 (November) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1881 (December) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1882 (January) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 1882 (February) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 1882 (March) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 1882 (April) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 1882 (May) (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 1882 (June) (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 1882 (September) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 1882 (November) (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 1883 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1884 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1885 (January) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1885 (February) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1885 (March) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1885 (April 1-15) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1885 (April 16-30) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1885 (May) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1885 (June) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1885 (July) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1885 (August 1-15) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1885 (August 16-31) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1885 (September) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1885 (October) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1885 (November) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1885 (December) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1886 (January) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1886 (February) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1886 (March) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1886 (April) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1886 (May) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1886 (June) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1886 (July) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1886 (August) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1886 (September) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1886 (October) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1886 (November) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1886 (December) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1887 (January-February) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1887 (July-August) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1887 (September-October) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1887 (November-December) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1888 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1889 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1890 (January) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1890 (May) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1890 (June) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 1890 (July) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - 1890 (August) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - 1890 (September) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - 1890 (October) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - 1890 (November) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - 1890 (December) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - 1891 (January) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1891 (February) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1891 (March) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1891 (April) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1891 (May) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1891 (June) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1891 (July) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1891 (August) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1891 (September) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1891 (October) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1891 (November) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 1891 (December) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - 1892 (January) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1892 (February) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1892 (March) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1892 (April) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1892 (May) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1892 (June) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1892 (July) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1892 (August) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 1892 (September) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - 1892 (October) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 1892 (November) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - 1892 (December) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - 1893 (January) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1893 (February) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1893 (March) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1893 (April) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1893 (May) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1893 (June) (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1893 (July) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1893 (August) (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1893 (September) (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 1893 (October) (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 1893 (November) (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 1893 (December) (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - 1894 (January) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1894 (February) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1894 (March) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1894 (April) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1894 (May) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1894 (June 1-20) (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1894 (June 21-30) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1894 (July 1-10) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1894 (July 11-18) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1894 (July 19-31) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1894 (August) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1894 (September) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1894 (October) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 1894 (November) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 1894 (December) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 1895 (January) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1895 (February) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1895 (March) (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 1895 (April) (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 1895 (May) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1895 (June) (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1895 (July) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 1895 (August) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - 1895 (September) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 1895 (October) (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - 1895 (November) (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - 1895 (December) (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - 1896 (January) (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1896 (February) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 1896 (March) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 1896 (April) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 1896 (May) (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 1896 (June) (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 1896 (July-September) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 1896 (October-December) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 1897 (January-February) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - 1897 (March-April) (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - 1897 (May) (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1897 (June) (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1897 (July) (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1897 (August) (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1897 (September) (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 1897 (October) (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 1897 (November) (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 1897 (December 1-15) (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - 1897 (December 16-31) (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - 1897-1902 (A) (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 1897-1902 (B) (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - 1897-1902 (C) (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 1897-1902 (D) (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 1897-1902 (E) (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 1897-1902 (F) (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 1897-1902 (G) (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - 1897-1902 (H-I) (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - 1897-1902 (J) (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - 1897-1902 (K) (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - 1897-1902 (L) (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - 1897-1902 (M) (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
  - 1897-1902 (N) (Box 14, Folder 15-16)
  - 1897-1902 (O) (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - 1897-1902 (P) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - 1897-1902 (R) (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - 1897-1902 (S) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - 1897-1902 (T-U-V) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - 1897-1902 (W) (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - 1898 (A) (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - 1898 (B) (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - 1898 (C) (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - 1898 (D) (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 1898 (E-F) (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - 1898 (G) (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - 1898 (H-I-J) (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - 1898 (K-L) (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - 1898 (M) (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - 1898 (N-O) (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - 1898 (P-Q) (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - 1898 (R) (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - 1898 (S) (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - 1898 (T-U-V) (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - 1898 (W) (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - 1900-1902 (A) (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - 1900-1902 (B) (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - 1900-1902 (C) (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - 1900-1902 (F) (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - 1900-1902 (G) (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - 1900-1902 (H) (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - 1900-1902 (I-J) (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - 1900-1902 (N-O) (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - 1898 (January) (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - 1898 (February) (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - 1898 (March) (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - 1898 (April) (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - 1898 (May-June) (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 1891 (July) (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - 1898 (August) (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - 1898 (September-October) (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - 1898 (November) (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - 1898 (December) (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - 1899 (January-February) (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - 1899 (March-April) (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - 1900 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 1901 (February-April) (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - 1901 (May) (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - 1901 (June) (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - 1901 (July) (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - 1901 (August) (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - 1901 (September) (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - 1901 (October) (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - 1901 (November) (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - 1901 (December) (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - 1902 (January) (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - 1902 (February) (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - 1902 (March) (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - 1902 (April) (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - 1902 (May) (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - 1902 (June) (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - 1902 (July) (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - 1902 (August) (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - 1902 (September) (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - 1902 (October) (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - 1902 (November) (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - 1902 (December) (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - 1903 (January) (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - 1903 (February) (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - 1903 (March) (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - 1903 (April) (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - 1903 (July) (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - 1904 (May) (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - 1904 (June) (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - 1904 (July 1-4) (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - 1904 (July 5-7) (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - 1904 (July 8-11) (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - 1904 (July 12-15) (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - 1904 (July 16-31) (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - 1904 (August) (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 1904 (September) (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - 1904 (October) (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - 1904 (November) (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - 1904 (December) (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - 1905 (January) (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - 1905 (February) (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - 1905 (March) (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - 1905 (April) (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - 1905 (May) (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - 1905 (June) (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - 1905 (July 1-15) (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - 1905 (July 16-31) (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - 1905 (August) (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - 1905 (September) (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - 1905 (October) (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - 1905 (November) (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - 1905 (December) (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - 1906 (January) (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - 1906 (February) (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - 1906 (March) (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 1906 (April) (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 1906 (May) (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - 1906 (June) (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - 1906 (July) (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - 1906 (August) (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - 1906 (September) (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - 1906 (October) (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - 1906 (November) (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - 1906 (December) (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - 1907 (January) (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - 1907 (February) (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - 1907 (March) (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - 1907 (April) (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - 1907 (May) (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - 1907 (June) (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - 1907 (July) (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - 1907 (September) (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - 1907 (October) (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - 1907 (November) (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - 1907 (December) (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - 1908 (January) (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - 1908 (February) (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - 1908 (March) (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - 1908 (April) (Box 20, Folder 27)
  - 1908 (June) (Box 20, Folder 28)
  - 1909 (Box 20, Folder 29)
  - 1910 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - 1911 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - 1912 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - 1914 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - 1915 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - 1916 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - 1917 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - 1918 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - 1919 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - 1920 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - 1921 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - 1922 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - 1924 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - 1925 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - 1930 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - 1931 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - 1932 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - 1933 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - 1934 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - 1935 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - 1936 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - 1937 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - 1938 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - 1939 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - 1940 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - 1941 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - 1942 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - 1943 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - 1944 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - 1945 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - 1946 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - 1948 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - 1949 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - 1962 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - 1966 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - 1970 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - n.d. (Box 22, Folder 17)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1783-1975., Extent: 40 boxes. (Box 23-62)
  The subject files contain a variety of information related to the business operations of Wallace and Son and The Wallace Company, and later activities of John G. Wallace II. Included are bills of lading, chattel property inventories, sales figures for Wallace produce, deeds, agreements and correspondence with the Dismal Swamp Land Company, estate papers, hands' accounts, lists of household expenses, insurance papers, memoranda, lighter load memoranda, which include names of vessels, item and amount shipped, consignee, and costs for labor and towing, merchandise accounts and inventories of products sold in the store at Wallaceton, patriotic society materials, contract work on the Dismal Swamp Canal, overseers' correspondence and reports, bank accounts, tax information (see also the Maps, Plans, and Drawings series), minutes, plats and surveys, title abstracts, product catalogs and equipment instructions, maps and tourist brochures, garden and seed catalogs, miscellaneous publications, oversized items, and ephemera.
  There is a large amount of material related to The Wallace Company and the failure of Bain and Brother, a banking house in Portsmouth, Virginia, including accounts of sales by its trustees, agreements, banks books, bills and answers, inventories, land descriptions, and promissory notes. Also included are papers documenting business dealings with the Richmond Cedar Works, including accounts, agreements, bills of lading, correspondence, estimates, inventories, lists, assets, and notes.
  Papers related to "Dover" and "Glencoe" farms include purchase inquiries, facts, boundaries, sharecropping agreements, loan papers with the Federal Land Bank of Baltimore, payroll, receipts and disbursements, production figures, shipment records, and information related to the sale to the U.S. government in 1941.
  There is also information related to the Northwest River Water Program in Chesapeake, Virginia in 1970. This was a dam construction project by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers. Included in the files are aerial photographs of the region.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Adams Express Company (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - Advertisement to Rent Glencoe, 1938 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Advertisement to Sell Dover, 1936-1940 (Box 23, Folder 4-6)
  - Agreements, 1846-1916 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Agricultural Adjustment Administration (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Agricultural Conference Board - Legislative Recommendations, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Allied Mills (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Altenheim Medical Dispensary, 1895 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - American Agricultural Chemical Company, 1940-1941 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - American Agriculturalist, 1895-1896 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - American Legion of Honor (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
  - American Legion of Honor - Assessments, 1883-1884 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - American Legion of Honor - Assessments, 1885-1886 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - American Legion of Honor - Assessments, 1887-1888 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - American Legion of Honor - Assessments, 1889-1890 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - American Legion of Honor - Assessments, 1891-1894 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - American Legion of Honor - By-Laws, Proceedings, Ribbons (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - American National Bank (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Angle Tract (Sexton Swamp) (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Atlantic Life Insurance Company (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Axle and Rim Accounts, 1883-1885 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Bain and Brother - Accounts of Sales for Trustees (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Bain and Brother - Agreements (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Bain and Brother - Bills and Answers (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Bain and Brother - Bank Protests (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Bain and Brother - Chattel Property Inventories (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Bain and Brother - Land Descriptions for Deeds (Drafts) (Box 25, Folder 6-7)
  - Bain and Brother - Lumber/Shingle Inventories (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Bain and Brother - Promissory Notes (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Bain and Brother - Trustees' Acounts (Box 25, Folder 10-11)
  - Baugh and Sons Fertilizers (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Bennett, Hendrickson and Company, 1895 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Bennett, Rand and Company, 1895 (Box 25, Folder 14)